Preliminary Guide to the Women's Studies Department records, 1965-1998 RG0093
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Women's Studies Department records
1965-1999
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
RG0093
4.00 Linear Feet
The Women's Studies Department at The George Washington University (GW) is responsible for several degrees for undergraduates, masters, and dual degrees. This collection includes committee meetings minutes, newsletters, proposals, comprehensive exams, and alumnae surveys. The materials range in date from 1965 to 1998.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 box 3 contains student records which are closed for the lifetime of the student, and are presumed open 75 years after date of creation.
Acquisition Information
The collection was transferred to the University Archives by the Women's Studies Department.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Women's Studies Department at The George Washington University (GW) is responsible for several degrees for undergraduates, masters, and dual degrees.
Founded in 1972, GW Women's Studies Program offered the first interdisciplinary M.A. degree in Women's Studies in the United States. This program grew from a highly successful Continuing Education for Women (CEW) project founded in 1965 and led by Professor Ruth Osborn. These CEW students, many of them college graduates influenced by the Women's Movement, wanted graduate work that would enable them to help other women. With demonstrated student demand, Dr. Osborn persuaded the administration to approve an interdisciplinary M.A. degree comparable to other Special Studies M.A. degrees in the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences. The first Women's Studies Master's Degree students entered the program in the 1973-1974 academic year.
In 1977, the GW Women's Studies Program took another groundbreaking step: the development of a public policy focus with the hiring of Dr. Virginia Allan, Chair of the 1969 Task Force on Women's Rights and Responsibilities, appointed by President Nixon and a retiring State Department official, joined by Dr. Phyllis Palmer, an American women's historian, and Charlotte Conable, a Women's Studies alumna. The public policy curriculum stressed a grounding in feminist theory, and encouraged student internships and related research projects as the degree's culmination. It trained graduates to change the social policies that constrained women's lives. Since 1982, the GW Women's Studies Program has offered two M.A. degrees sharing the same Women's Studies core courses, the M.A. in Public Policy with a Concentration in Women's Studies, and the M.A. in Women's Studies with a liberal arts concentration.
Recent innovations at the graduate level include the establishment of a field in Gender and Social Policy within the interdisciplinary Ph.D. in Public Policy in 1997, and then, a year later, a Ph.D. in Human Sciences with an M.A. in Women's Studies. In May 1997, the George Washington University Public Policy and Women's Studies programs joined in affiliation with the Institute for Women's Policy Research (IWPR), an independent, non-profit research organization.
In 2000, the department added several joint degrees between the Law School and Women's Studies, making this department one of two programs nationwide to offers such degrees.
At the undergraduate level, a Women's Studies Minor was inaugurated in 1989 and a major as well as two 5 year M.A./B.A. programs were added in 2000.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection includes committee meetings minutes, newsletters, proposals, comprehensive exams, and alumnae surveys. The materials range in date from 1965 to 1998. The collection was transferred to the University Archives by the Women's Studies Department. Formerly RG10.8.
Collection Organization
Organized in two series of departmental files.
Public policy; Feminist theory; Foggy Bottom (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.); George Washington University. Graduate School of Arts and Sciences; George Washington University; Institute for Women's Policy Research; George Washington University. Women's Studies Program and Policy Center
- Departmental files, 1974-1986; RG0093 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  The materials of this series contain committee meetings, newsletters, proposals, comprehensive exams, and alumni surveys. The materials range in date from 1974 to 1986.
  Formerly ACC#69
  - Women's Studies: Program Outline and History, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Women's Studies: Committee, Members' Biographies, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Women's Studies: Committee Meetings, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Women's Studies: Committee Meetings, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women's Studies: Committee Meetings, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Women's Studies: Committee Meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Women's Studies: Committee Meetings, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Women's Studies: Committee Minutes, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Staff Meetings, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Candidates for Alumnae Advisory Board, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Women's Studies Graduates and Alumnae Group, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - GWU Faculty Senate Meetings, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Women's Studies: Library Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - President's Advisory Committee for Women, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Steering Committee: Women's Studies, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Women's Studies: Steering Committee, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Steering Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Steering Committee, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Response from Student Advisory Board, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Women's Studies: Student Advisory Board, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Women's Studies: Newsletters, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Original Newsletters, 07/1977 ca. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Women's Studies: Newsletters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    General note
    Originals
  - Women's Studies: Newsletters, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Women's Studies: Newsletters, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Women's Studies: Newsletters, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Women's Studies: Newsletters, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Women's Studies: Newsletter, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - The Apple, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Brochure Survey, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Women's Studies Brochures, 1980 ca. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Publicity: Flyers, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Fund-Raising, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Press Releases, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Newspaper Articles: Publicity, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Advertisements Placed in Publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Women's Studies: Publicity, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Library Exhibit, 03/1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Women's Studies: Colloquia and Events, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Women's Activities in Creative Arts, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Women's Studies: Activities, 1977 ca. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Women's Studies: Colloquia, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Women's Studies: Activities, 08/1977 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Women's Studies: Move, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Women's Studies: Activities [1/2], 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Women's Studies: Activities [2/2], 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Theater Benefit, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Works in Progress, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Funding: Rockefeller-Levy correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Older Women: Research Coalition, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Proposals: International, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Roundtable on Working Women: WSP and NCWW, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Proposal: WSP, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - WSTU Newsletter, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Women in the World Events, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Older Women: Policy Forum, 02/27/1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Caucus: Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    WSPPC - WREI - CC
  - Older Women: Report on Distribution, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Older Women: Symposium, 08/04/1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Women and Retirement: Income Policy, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Women and Social Security Reform, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Publications: Newsletter Heading, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Original
  - Media Project: Advisory Board, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Media'Project, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - WSPPC Grant Proposals, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The Women's Delegation from the People's Republic of China, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 10th Birthday Party: Exhibit and Directory, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Undergraduate WSTU, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Development and Administration of WSTU, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Controversies, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - From the Apple to the Archive, 1974 ca. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Alumnae Employment Survey, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Alumnae Survey, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Alumnae Survey, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 5 Year Plan, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 5 Year Planning Document, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Evaluation Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Statement of Course Books and Supplies, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Masters: Promotion, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Women's Studies Information Form, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Women's Studies: Orientation, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Questionaire: Research on Women's Issues, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Non-Credit Course Activities, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Virginia R. Allan Full Partnership Fund, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Women in News: Project, 1981-1983 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Action, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Revson Budget and Ford, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Revson Proposal and Agreements, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Comprehensives questions and some graded student responses, 1975-1986; 24 folder(s) (Box 3)
    Conditions Governing Access
    This box contains student records, which are restricted for the lifetime of the student and are presumed open 75 years after the date of creation.
- Departmental files, 1965-1998; RG0093 Series 2; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series contains newsletters, memorandums, brochures, flyers, invitations, press releases, and reports. They range in date from 1965 to 1998. The materials concern the Women's Studies program, courses, human rights, history, exhibits, WOMANSPACE (Women's Center), Women's Studies Student Organization, lectures, the Virginia allan fund, Women in the World luncheons, the Women's Studies Program and Policy Center, registration, internships, "Older Women: the Economics of Aging", fellowships, conferences, the Committee of Women Studies, the New Horizons for Women program, "Development and Administration of Women's Studies July 1970-July 1975", twenty-fifth anniversary, and "Martha's Rag" newsletter.
  Formerly vertical files
  - Women's Studies, 08/1973-1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Women's Studies History, 10/1965-1998 -- --ca. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Women's Studies Newsletter Martha's Rag, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Publications, 1967-1999; RG0093 Series 3
  Scope and Contents
  Materials were transferred by the Women's, Gender and Sexuality Studies (WGSS) department. All publications were kept in their small library and document the women's movement.
  - Women's Studies Quarterly, 1981-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Women: A Journal of Liberation, 1969-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
  - Women's International Network News (WIN), 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - National Women's Studies Association Newsletter, 1983-1996 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - SAGE: A Scholarly Journal on Black Women, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Topics: Women as writers; workers; Africa and the Diaspora; artists and artisans
  - The Black Scholar, 1985-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lilith: The Jewish Women's Quarterly, 1976-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Imprint: The Gospel According to Lilith, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ISIS International Bulletin, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Washington Equal Times, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
  - Equal Times - Northern Virginia, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Commonwomon: A Wild Woman's Periodical, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Off Our Backs: A Women's Newsjournal, 1983-1999 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - National Times, 1989-1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Publications, 1977-1985 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    The Chicana Feminist, 1977 Women in the Global Factory, 1983 Daughters of Sarah, 1985
  - Radical America: 15 Years of Radical America - an Anthology, Vol. 16, No. 3, May-June 1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Politics of Matriarchy, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Publications, 1972-1995 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Wise Women's News, 1994-1995 The Power of Women and the Subversion of the Community, with an introduction by Selma James, 1972 Sex, Race and Class by Selma James, 1975 Bread and Roses America's first unfinished revolution, 1976
  - Iris (1982); Mother Jones (1997), 1982-1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Notes from the Third Year: Women's Liberation, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Redstockings: Feminist Revolution, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Goddard-Cambridge Magazine Feminist Studies issue (1976); Le Bardache (1981), 1976-1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Negro Women in the Population and in the Labor Force, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - motive: lesbian/feminist issue, vol. 32, no. 1, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - The Erotization of Male Dominance Female Submission, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - A Journal of Women's Mysteries: The Beltane Papers, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rethinking Columbus: Teaching about the 500th Anniversary of Columbus's arrival in America, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Boston News, Winter 1992 (Box 3)
  - Sojourner: A Women's Forum newspaper, 1984-1992 (Box 3)